RAHUL MURMURIA

10524 Rosehaven Street, Apt. 204, Fairfax, VA 22030 Email: rahul@murmuria.in | Phone: (703) 474-1261

PROFILE

Researcher, programmer, and data scientist with over 10 years of experience building prototypes and MVPs. Ph.D. candidate in Computer Science at George Mason University, Fairfax, Virginia. Co-inventor of a patent-applied technology to continuously authenticate users on a smartphone by modeling their physical behavior using machine learning techniques.

Specialities: Algorithm Design, Exploratory Data Analytics, Hypothesis Testing, Inferential Statistics, Descriptive Analytics, Cluster Analysis, Anomaly Detection, Predictive Analytics, Regression, Linear Programming, Time-Series Analysis, Data Visualization, Performance Analysis, Complexity Analysis, Data Structures, Parallel and Distributed Programming, Code Version Controlling.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Algorithm Engineer, Kryptowire, Fairfax, VA

June 2015-present

- Fulfilled the technical requirements of a DARPA grant for the Active Authentication project by developing the analytics and prototype implementation
- Managed the data collection process involving 110 participants, prepared analytics using novel machine learning algorithms, and contributed to the final report and other grant proposals extending this work
- Implemented a prototype on Android devices that performs data collection, model generation, and continuous authentication score computation entirely on-device (Patent filed)

Research Assistant, Center for Assurance Research and Engineering, Fairfax, VA

January 2010–May 2015

- Prepared a regression model on Android smartphones to predict battery power consumption using multi-dimensional system resources measurements, achieving a granularity of as low as 1 kernel jiffy in time
- Conducted performance analysis of a custom fuse-based encrypted filesystem for Android devices; Developed the login process and the secure-wipe which was deployed by DARPA into devices used by the military
- Supervised 3 Ph.D. students to create a UX testing tool for Android devices

Technology Consultant, Federal Trade Commission, Washington D.C.

May 2013-July 2013

- Provided technical expertise and guidance as the FTC attorneys performed research in the mobile app stores and analyzed potentially fraudulent mobile applications
- Developed ways to automate some of the processes of preparing technical evidence

Teaching Assistant, George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

August 2012–May 2013

• Conducted classroom lectures and prepared homework assignments for graduate-level courses: Security Lab, Intrusion Detection, Network Security, and OS Security

System Administrator, George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

October 2008–January 2010

• Provided second tier technical support to the School of Engineering

Offshore Web Developer, Openworld, Washington D.C.

September 2005–May 2007

• Built a web portal for online marketplace of telework services

EDUCATION

Doctorate of Philosophy in Computer Science (All But Dissertation)

Summer 2017

George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

Proposal - Modeling User Behavior for Context Generation on Mobile Devices

GPA 3.54

Master of Science in Computer Engineering

George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

 $\begin{array}{c} {\rm December}\ 2010 \\ {\rm GPA}\ 3.8 \end{array}$

Thesis - Energy Profiling and Control for Android Devices

May 2008

Bachelor of Technology in *Computer Engineering* National Institute of Technology, Jaipur, India

Project - Glendix: A Plan 9 / Linux Distribution

GPA 7.08 / 10.0

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming and Markup Languages: Python, Java, LATEX, Bash, C, C++, PHP, Javascript, Lisp

Data Handling: SQL, NoSQL, Pandas, HDF5, CSV, JSON, XML

Statistical Analysis Tools: Scikit-learn, Weka, Matlab, Apache Commons Math, Eigen

Visualization Tools: Matplotlib, Seaborn, Tableau, Gnuplot

Other Tools and API: Volatility, Valgrind, gprof, DDMS, Beautiful Soup, Snort, Wireshark

ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

System Administrator, National Institute of Technology, Jaipur, India

November 2005-February 2008

- Taught system administration, web scripting, and general programming to 75+ students in a weekend workshop series spanning 2 semesters
- Mentored 10+ students to actively contribute to open source projects within the University
- Developed the University's first electronic course registration system which included some back-office functions, thereby saving the faculty, staff, and students 5000+ man-hours every semester

PATENTS

A. Stavrou, R. Murmuria, R. Johnson, D. Barbara. Active Authentication of Users. USPTO Application 15236049, filed August 2016. Patent Pending.

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers

- 1. R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, D. Barbara, D. Fleck. Continuous Authentication on Mobile Devices Using Power Consumption, Touch Gestures and Physical Movement of Users. Research in Attacks, Intrusions, and Defenses (RAID), pp. 405–424. Springer, 2015.
- 2. R. Murmuria, J. Medsger, A. Stavrou, J.M. Voas. Mobile Application and Device Power Usage Measurements. Sixth International Conference on Software Security and Reliability (SERE), pp. 147–156. IEEE, 2012.
- 3. Z. Wang, R. Johnson, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou. Exposing Security Risks for Commercial Mobile Devices. *International Conference on Mathematical Methods*, Models, and Architectures for Computer Network Security (MMM-ACNS), pp. 3–21. Springer, 2012.
- 4. Z. Wang, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou. Implementing and optimizing an encryption filesystem on android. 13th International Conference on Mobile Data Management (MDM), pp. 52–62. IEEE, 2012.

Workshop Papers

- R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, D. Barbara, V. Sritapan. Your Data in Your Hands: Privacy-preserving User Behavior Models for Context Computation. *International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom)*, IEEE, 2017.
- 6. R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou. Authentication Feature and Model Selection using Penalty Algorithms. Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS), USENIX, 2016.

White Papers

- 7. R. Martin, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, N. Nazzicari. MokA: Mobile k-Anonymity (Sender Anonymity Over Untrusted Mobile Network Operators). 2010.
- 8. M. S. Gaur, A. Narayanan, R. Murmuria. Comparative Analytic Simulation of Peer to Peer Networks. 2007.

Tutorials

- 9. R. Johnson, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, V. Sritapan. Pairing Continuous Authentication with Proactive Platform Hardening. International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom), IEEE, 2017.
- 10. A. Narayanan, R. Narasimhan, R. Murmuria, M. Gaur. Institutional Information Management using Open Source Technologies. 1st International Conference on Digital Information Management, IEEE, 2006.

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Reviewer: ACNS 2011, QRS 2015, Elsevier Journal Micropro, International Journal for Information Security Member: IAENG, IEEE, IEEE Computer Society, USENIX, Data Community DC, ACM Washington DC, DataKind DC